<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Comments on RIRSC</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/comments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Comments on RIRSC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ricardo López</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 10:24:30 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/comments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>http://localhost:1313/Rirsc_Logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Cactus Comments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/switching_to_cactus_comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 10:24:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/switching_to_cactus_comments/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Commento for a while for comments (without much adoption to be honest), and while I really love the project, and the simplicity of its approach, there&rsquo;s always been one unavoidable thing I never really liked too much: if you want to comment, you have to register to my commento instance.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s less than ideal, considering that if I did have lots of people who wanted to comment, that&rsquo;d have been quite a strain on my humble home server, where my commento instance is hosted.</p>
<p>Today I found <a href="https://karmanyaah.malhotra.cc/tech/2021/06/website-things/">this post</a> on Mastodon (feel free to <a href="https://linuxrocks.online/@gabmus">follow me there</a> by the way) by Karmanyaah Malhotra about how he reworked his website recently. I always enjoy reading about other people&rsquo;s websites, so I quickly read through it, just to find out about this comment system called <a href="https://cactus.chat">Cactus Comments</a>.</p>
<p>Cactus Comments uses <a href="https://matrix.org/">Matrix</a> to create a federated comment section on your website. If you have a Matrix account on any instance, you can comment on Cactus! Heck you can even use a full-fledged Matrix client to do so! That&rsquo;s just great.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s free to use and self hostable as well, so there&rsquo;s really not much of an excuse not to try it out. Plus if you already have a Matrix account you&rsquo;re already halfway there.</p>
<p>I integrated it in my <a href="https://gitlab.com/gabmus/hugo-ficurinia">Ficurinia Hugo theme</a> without much effort, so there&rsquo;s another bonus point.</p>
<p>And that&rsquo;s it, I&rsquo;m really happy about this new comment system, it&rsquo;s one less service running on my home server and due to its decentralized and federated nature it will hopefully encourage more people to leave interesting comments and get a conversation going!</p>
]]></description>
      
        <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:1313/images/post_pics/Switching_to_Cactus_Comments/cactus.avif" />
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On privacy conscious comments and analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/on_comments_and_analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/on_comments_and_analytics/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>This blog is fairly new, and so I still have to set up everything. Comments are obviously a very important part of a blog, especially if you want any kind of feedback on the stuff you&rsquo;re doing.</p>
<p>The lazy solution is pretty obvious: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disqus#Criticism,_privacy,_and_security_concerns"><em>Disqus</em> the privacy nightmare</a>.</p>
<p>I like the wild idea of respecting my readers&rsquo; privacy, and so I started looking for alternative solutions.</p>
<p>The one solution I chose to adopt is an open source comment platform called <a href="https://commento.io/"><strong>Commento</strong></a>. It works just like Disqus, except since it doesn&rsquo;t make money from violating people&rsquo;s privacy, you can&rsquo;t really use it for free.</p>
<p>You can either choose to pay what you want for it (with a minimum of 3 USD) or host it yourself.</p>
<p>I already pay for a VPS for <a href="https://techpills.technology">Tech Pills&rsquo; website</a>, but it&rsquo;s not subject to heavy load, so a service more running on it wouldn&rsquo;t really hurt.</p>
<p>You can install Commento using <code>docker-compose</code>, which is very convenient. I made some changes to the <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file to better suit my needs, and put an nginx reverse proxy in front of it to add https into the mix.</p>
<p>After writing some CSS to adapt it to the blog&rsquo;s theme, the new comment box is ready to roll.</p>
<p>As a nice (unexpected) bonus, Commento also provides some basic analytics like total page views and number of comments. And that&rsquo;s all totally anonymous, it&rsquo;s just a faceless number that&rsquo;s not associated to any identity.</p>
<p>And that&rsquo;s about it, if you&rsquo;re looking for a privacy respecting, open source, powerful comment platform, that&rsquo;s also pretty easy to install and offers some bonus analytics on top, Commento is the way to go.</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
