<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Tech on rirsc</title>
    <link>http://192.168.178.34:1313/tags/tech/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tech on rirsc</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ricardo López</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://192.168.178.34:1313/tags/tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>http://192.168.178.34:1313/icons/risc_logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Broligarchs doesnt speak for Dave (ratfactor)</title>
      <link>http://192.168.178.34:1313/posts/25/250322_broligarchs-doesnt-speak-for-dave-ratfactor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.168.178.34:1313/posts/25/250322_broligarchs-doesnt-speak-for-dave-ratfactor/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I stick up heavily for Dave <a href="https://ratfactor.com/"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



(ratfactor)&#8599</a>
 





 and his profound defence on why <a href="https://ratfactor.com/tech-nope"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



‘broligarchs’ doesnt speak for him&#8599</a>
 





</p>
<p>These are the types of words that I save and revisit constantly. It represents my view in 99%. Full of truths and explains in detail a lot of the current tech problems. Here I selected a few quotes, but please make some time to read the entire text.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Tech&rdquo;, as portrayed in the public eye right now is something I barely recognize. It’s almost universally negative: Social media, ad tech, blockchain, &lsquo;AI&rsquo;. I don’t work on any of that stuff. Am I even part of the same industry? (I don’t actually have an answer to that question.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The trans community is small and vulnerable, which is exactly why they are being targeted. Which is all the more reason attacking them or attempting to erase them from history, like our government is doing, is gutless, spineless, brainless, and heartless. <strong>The transgender computer geeks are, by volume, some of the most creative, interesting, and prolific contributors we’ve ever had.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<!-- READ MORE! -->
<blockquote>
<p>The most visible and most rancid pieces of flesh plastered on tech’s grinning skull are the megalomaniacs behind each decision, the greedy scumbags that would turn our computers against us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These big tech bros may claim to want free markets and individual liberty but make no mistake: <strong>What they seek is the &ldquo;freedom&rdquo; to take every single cent of wealth from every single market on Earth and the &ldquo;liberty&rdquo; to use their enormous wealth</strong> and also the law to pull the ladder up behind them to make sure no one can ever, ever follow them up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These are the same people who want to make your car play an advertisement while you’re at a stoplight or have your TV harvest your viewing habits to sell to the highest bidder or make it impossible to own any digital goods so you have to rent them for a monthly fee forever.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I’m telling you, it doesn’t have to be this way.</p>
<p>I know it can be better because I’m living it.</p>
<p>I want everyone to have the same computer experience I have right now. I run a free operating system that serves no ads and does not update unless I explicitly tell it to. I trust the software tools I use because they are written by fellow enthusiasts. I visit ad-free websites. My computer hardware is cheap and plentiful. <strong>The computer serves me, not the other way around</strong> and I call the shots on everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Listen to a big tech billionaire talk about any subject outside of their field of business. It’s ridiculous to the point of parody. It pierces the idea that these guys are geniuses. They’re clever and utterly ruthless. They’re willing to exploit things the rest of us wouldn’t. But the idea that they’re all geniuses is a myth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My heroes don’t break or bend laws to make a buck, use their power to bully people, or think it would be cool to be feudal lords over a frightened populace of vassals. <strong>My heroes create things and share what they know and they stand up for others.</strong><br>
<br>
The broligarchs are not techie culture. They are not our leaders. They have nothing in common with us. They are vultures. They don’t speak for us.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As mentioned, this is just a quick selection from all the gems poured into the text. Bold text on quotes are mine.</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
