<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Neovim on RIRSC</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/neovim/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Neovim on RIRSC</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Ricardo López</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 07:36:27 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/neovim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>http://localhost:1313/Rirsc_Logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Nvpunk: A Modern Neovim Distribution with Batteries Included</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/221206_nvpunk_a_modern_neovim_distribution_with_batteries_included/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 07:36:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/221206_nvpunk_a_modern_neovim_distribution_with_batteries_included/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using <a href="https://neovim.io"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



neovim&#8599</a>












 for a while now, and for me, it&rsquo;s the single best text editor out there.</p>
<p>But it&rsquo;s got a big problem: it&rsquo;s a bit of a hassle, and you have to know what you&rsquo;re doing. There&rsquo;s a wide ecosystem of plugins that integrate into each other, most of them requiring custom configuration code to work. It took a while, but I managed to put together a pretty good config.</p>
<p>Over time this config, that was initially living in my dotfiles repo, grew larger and more complex. So came the refactorings, then the generalizations, modularization, custom settings systems&hellip;</p>
<p>It outgrew its role as a humble user config, it became its own thing. At some point I had to give it its own repo, and along with it, a proper name: <strong>Nvpunk</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/images/post_pics/nvpunk_a_modern_neovim_distribution_with_batteries_included/greeter.jpg" alt="Screenshot of Nvpunk’s greeter"></p>
<p>Yeah, that sounds about right.</p>
<hr>
<p>Romantic storytelling aside, let me tell you what Nvpunk is: a complete, out of the box and ready to go neovim distribution.</p>
<p>In other words, it&rsquo;s a fully featured neovim configuration you can use without having to learn how to select, install and manage plugins, and maintain the configuration glue that holds it all together.</p>
<p>Some highlights of what&rsquo;s included:</p>
<ul>
<li>LSP support with completions, snippets, diagnostics and formatting</li>
<li>DAP support for debugging with a familiar UI</li>
<li>Advanced syntax highlighting with TreeSitter</li>
<li>Interactive file tree with git support</li>
<li>Code outline panel</li>
<li>Fancy greeter with customizable header graphics</li>
<li>Theme chooser with a selection of popular preconfigured themes</li>
<li>Categorized right click menu to access some useful features</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been heavily inspired by other projects like <a href="https://www.lunarvim.org/"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



LunarVim&#8599</a>












, <a href="https://nvchad.com/"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



NvChad&#8599</a>












 and <a href="https://astronvim.github.io/"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



AstroNvim&#8599</a>












, with the difference that Nvpunk tries to offer a ready to go experience, while these distros give you more of a base to build on yourself, still requiring manual configuration to be effective.</p>
<p>Nvpunk still offers some degree of custom configuration, but it&rsquo;s more tailored towards advanced users that know what they&rsquo;re doing, and it&rsquo;s very much optional.</p>
<p>Most of the things you may want to change are configurable via a UI preferences menu, accessible from the greeter.</p>
<p>I understand that Nvpunk may not be for everyone: some may call it bloated, and typically (neo)vim fans like to roll their own config anyway (just like I did), but that&rsquo;s fine. Nvpunk is mostly targeted at people that are looking for a good, feature-rich text editor, but that don&rsquo;t have the time, interest or knowledge to maintain their own config.</p>
<p>You can find out more on <a href="https://nvpunk.gabmus.org"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



Nvpunk&rsquo;s website&#8599</a>












 and on the <a href="https://gitlab.com/gabmus/nvpunk"
 target="_blank" rel="noopener" >



GitLab repository&#8599</a>












.</p>
]]></description>
      
        <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:1313/images/post_pics/nvpunk_a_modern_neovim_distribution_with_batteries_included/cover.jpg" />
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
